<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Strange ne[w]es</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1606</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 12 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18007</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4658</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117079</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852294</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852294</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17610</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18007)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17610)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1130:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Strange ne[w]es</title>
                  <author>Gresham, Edward.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by R. B[lower]] for G. Vincent and W. Blackwal and are to be sold at Guildhall gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1606]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Subsidiary title page reads: Strange fearful &amp; true newes, which hapned at Carlstadt, in the kingdome of Croatia. .. Translated out of the Dutch coppie, printed at Vienna in Austria".</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from imprint on subsidiary title page.</note>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: Ed. Gresham.</note>
                  <note>Title page is a folded leaf; fold occurs through the "w" of "newes".</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B⁴ (-A1, B4, blanks?).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Preface dated 11 Feb. 1605 [o.s.]; year of publication confirmed by STC.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Apparitions --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:17610:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17610:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>STRANGE NEVES.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>At London printed for G. Vincent and W. Blackwal and are to be ſold at Guildhall gate.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:17610:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17610:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HAT Credit this ſtraunge Report may pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe (Gentle reader) is a thing I greatly reſpect not, and much leſſe contend for: yet, thus much let me tell thee, it had th'pprobation of ſome, both of good iudgment, and ſtaide diſcretion, and of ſuch Place and Condition, as may ſuperſeede all ſuſpition of vaine or idle impoſitions. And for my part, this I dare aſſure thee, it agreeth in all poyntes, with the <hi>High Dutch Coppie,</hi> whence it was tranſlated: firſt printed at VIENA in <hi>Auſtria,</hi> which for my better ſatiſfac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion I cauſed to bee brought vnto mee, and diligently conferd them togither, before reſolued Opinion, being no leſſe ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous then any to giue furtherance to any matter, eyther of falſe or friuolous import, a thing neyther ſuting the ſtate of theſe tymes, not ſorting mine owne condition. Now for my opinion herein; The playneſſe of the Style wherein it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> written, voide of <hi>Ambages,</hi> Amplifications, and all other. Vaine flouriſhes (ſuch as nimble wits, might very eaſily haue inueſted ſuch a Subiect withall) is to me no ſmall argument of the verity thereof: The prodigjes themſelus alſo, iuſt as wel in matter as manner ſorting the nature and diſpoſition or theſe tymes, both touching their generation and forme, and apt repreſentation of the Euents by them preſignified.</p>
            <p>But admit the verity and ſtrangnes too (as indeed it is both ſtrang &amp; horrible) yet ſo long, hath bin the conti<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ante of happy and acceptable times, without any great or notable
<pb facs="tcp:17610:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
taſt of contrarietie, that wee thinke they will neuer haue end, neyther fearing chaung, nor crediting any thing that may giue occaſion of ſuch doubt: not much vnlike the <hi>Iſralites,</hi> (God in mercy a little differing the'xecution of his iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts denounced by the Prophets <hi>Ieremy</hi> &amp; <hi>Ezekiel</hi>) growing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſo conſtant conceipt of ſetled ſecuritie, that they neyther credited viſion, nor feared the event thereof: holding for vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted truth, that neyther was ſuch viſions of any effect, nor any ſuch thing ſhoulde happen vnto them, or like thoſe in the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> time, who becauſe they ſaw neyther chaung, nor likelyhood of chaung of times, before or after them, could hardly entertaine the credit of ſuch things as was ſpoken tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the miſteries of mans redemption. But this is to abuſe times bountie, &amp; the long ſuffering of the great God of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, who a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he anſwered the one, the dayes are at hand, and the effect of euery viſion: there ſhall be no more ſuch a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerb amongſt you, for no viſions ſhall be any more in vayne, nor diuinations miſeffectuall: Th'other. There was an age be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, for like ſinne and corruption deſtroyed and periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the general deluge, ſo wil he quit our miſconſtruction of his louing kindnes &amp; good patience with ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>odayne &amp; imminent vengeance, an argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t whereof may be this, &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more prodigious Oſtenrs partly paſt and many more yet to come, &amp; ſome now imminent. &amp; ſurely this I dare be bold to ſay. If theſe mundane &amp; moueable bodies be mutually im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsiue &amp; impreſsible, nature conſtant in her Periods &amp; rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon experience &amp; Iugme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in man, be of any power or credit. The great coniunction of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> two ſuperior bodies <hi>Saturne</hi> and <hi>Iupiter,</hi> conſtipated with ſo many ſeuerall coniunctions and radiations of other planets, and in the ſame place very neare, in parle together as it were for ſome ſtrange decree of great conſequence. The Earth's and Moones late and horrible obſcurations, the freque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Ecclipſations of the fixed bodyes; by the wandring, the fixed ſtars, I meane with the planets,
<pb facs="tcp:17610:3"/>
within theſe fewe yeares more then ordinary, ſhall without doubt (ſalued diuine inhibytion) haue their effects no leſſe admirable, then the poſitiues vnuſuall. Which PEVCER with many more too long to reharſe out of continuall obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation and the conſent of all Authors noted to be, new Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues, Trayterous Deſignements, Catching at Kingdomes, tranſlation of Empyre, downefall of menn in Authoritye, aemulation, Ambition, Innouatious, Factious Sects, Schiſms and much diſturbance and trobles in religion and matters of the Church, with many other thinges infallible, in ſequent ſuch orbicall poſition and Phaenomenes. Examples and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances whereof he ſetteth downe many both out of his owne experience and hiſtories of diuers ages, wherein Mirald us alſo is ſo conſtant, that he peremtorily concludeth, <hi>Regnorum fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tales mutationes, effectus grandes, et caſus notabiles nunquam conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſſe, quin cauſa aliqua coelestis, et praemonstratio ceu de claſsico ill<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s notis ante ce<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inerint, et quaſi digito ostenderent,</hi> &amp; MANILIVS <hi>nunquam futilibus excanduit ignibus aer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seing then y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo many praemo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of fearful euent, as theſe ſtraung diſpoſitions of mundane bodies, this and many more prodigious oſtents, ſome paſt, &amp; more to come (as I ſaid (are yet as it were before our Eies, it ſhall not bee amiſſe with the prouident &amp; vigilant Ante, whileſt it is yet Summer &amp; Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt, to prouide for the neceſſitie of Winter, leaſt, with <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> idle foole, whileſt we ſleep and ſlumber, and folde our handes: yet a little, and yet a little, in the affiance of our miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceiued ſecuritie, miſery come vpon vs, as one trauelling by the way, &amp; neceſsitie like an armed man.</p>
            <p>And thus commending all to thy beſt conſtruction, I reſt</p>
            <p>From my houſe the George next <hi>Dyers Hall</hi> in Thames ſtreet. London February 11 1605.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in all honeſt offices,
Ed. Greſham.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17610:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17610:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>STRANGE fearful &amp; true newes, which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned at CARLSTADT, in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of CROATIA.</p>
            <p>DECLARING HOW THE Sunne did ſhine like <hi>Bloude</hi> nine dayes toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and how two Armies were ſeene in the <hi>Ayre,</hi> the one encountring the other.</p>
            <p>And how alſo a Woman was deliuered of three prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <hi>gious ſonnes,, which Prophiſied many ſtrange &amp; fearefull</hi> thinges, which ſhould ſhortly come to paſſe, All which happened the twelfth of Iune, laſt, 1605. which is the 2 day of the moneth, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our computation.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of the Dutch Coppie, Printed at VIENNA in <hi>Auſtria.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. B.</hi> for G. Vincent and VV, Blackwall, &amp; are to be ſolde ouer againſt Guild-hall Gate.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:17610:5"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:17610:5"/>
            <head>NEWES From Carlſtadt, in the Knigdome of Croatia in Germanie.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>ARKE</hi> and conſider wel with your ſelues deere <hi>Chriſtians</hi> (both Rich &amp; Poore) of what eſtate or degr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap> you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, and ſake all the mean <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> that poſſible y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an to a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>nd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es: for that the Lorde ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>yl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ten vs more and more, and ſheweth vs his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>y <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d which he intendeth to punniſh vs withall, for our moſt foule and wicked ſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which we c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>to more and m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e, but we reg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d it not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing at all.</p>
            <p>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>GOD,</hi> 160<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Inhabitants of <hi>Carl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>adt</hi> were much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in great perple<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ie: for t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t the Sunn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>d right <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> their Church, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> about (as it plainly appeared <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and fearfu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſight, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of many people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oh, deare Breethren and Chriſtians all,</hi> l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſpect to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>GOD</hi> hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:17610:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
dayes together, as it were in red <hi>bloud,</hi> hauing on the one ſide <hi>Moones &amp; Turkiſh S<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bells:</hi> and on the other ſide great <hi>Ordinance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Citizens of Carlſtadt</hi> were mightely affrayde at the ſight hereof, which hapned on a Sunday, (being the t<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elfth of <hi>Ivne</hi> as aforeſaid) On which day alſo, was ſéene too great Armys of men of warre, encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring one another in the Ayre, with ſuch wonderfull noyce, that the ſame was heard vppon the Earth, as ſounding of Trumpets, and ſuch like. And had theire <hi>Enſignes</hi> and <hi>Standers</hi> with <hi>Starres</hi> and halfe <hi>Moones</hi> as the Turkes do vſe.</p>
            <p>The whole Commonaltie both great and ſmall, did wring their handes at the ſight hereof, ſo did they alſo, that dwelled far of, &amp; then preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly was ſéen a great Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie of Chriſtians in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ayre, ready to reſiſt the Turks.</p>
            <p>No Emperour or King, did euer fight ſuch a battaile as there was ſeene in the Ayre: There were <hi>Spiritual men</hi> ſéene in the Chriſtian Armie, and many flaine of the <hi>Turkes</hi> and <hi>Infidels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There a man might haue ſéene ſuch running &amp; Ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the <hi>Turkes,</hi> that the people were al aſtoniſhed, for all the Turkiſh horſes did run vp to the knees in the <hi>Chriſtians bloud.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But beholde the wonderfull woorkes of <hi>Almighty God,</hi> for when the battaile began, [which was from the Euening, till thr<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of the Clocke in the Morning] and then the <hi>Moone</hi> did loſe her light and the Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men vaniſhed quite away. <hi>But yeat marke what hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Woman was heard in the ſame Citiy to trauell in <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>earing of child <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> together: And
<pb facs="tcp:17610:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
then a ſtrange thing was ſéene in the Ayre, for ſhe was deliuered of three Sonnes, <hi>as in the Picture is to bee ſeene.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt of theyſe Prodigious Children had foure heads, which ſpake and vttred ſtrange things. The ſecond Child was black like a More, &amp; the third Chyld like vnto Death.</p>
            <p>The Child with foure heads, began to crye a loud, and many women rann to heare it, one of the heads ſaid with high voice: <hi>There ſhall ſhortly many Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians be ſlayne by the Turkes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond head ſaid: <hi>All the wonders of the Turks which you haue ſeene in the Ayre: Shall all come too paſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Turk with many Tartars, ſhall overcome all Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garie, euen to Auſtria, and Morauia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third head ſaid. <hi>The Emperour, Kings Earles and Lords, ſhall then ariſe, and ſhall put the Turke to flight.</hi> The fourth head ſaid, <hi>before that come to paſſe, ſtrange wonders ſhall appeare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The black Child began to cry a loud, <hi>a time of dearth is at hand, both here and in other places, which ſhall not eſcape you, men ſhall periſh for hunger, and great want ſhall be of corne and graine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third Child began to crye, <hi>repent and amend your liues, before death do catch hold on you, this Chyld was like vnto Death to ſee to, and ſaid for certa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine great death and mortality ſhall come ouer poore and Rich.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Come hither both young and olde, ſayd the black child, remember theſe words here ſpoken and conceals them not, <hi>many great wonders ſhall be ſeene, before</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:17610:7"/>
               <hi>one thouſand &amp; ten be written: Shall all come to paſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe three Children, hauing ſpoken theſe things, died anon after. Euery man wondred, and the people were altogether aſtoniſhed, and mooued to the hart, with the ſtrangenes of this Prophecy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let vs pray to God for grace, and call vpon his holy name, both e<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rly and late, that we abſtaine from ſinne, and amend our liues, for the d<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y of the Lord is at hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:17610:7"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
